Else von Richthofen Collection MS008
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
- Letters and correspondence, 1898 -- 1947; 1900 -- 1915; MS008.001; 0.75 Linear Feet; 190 Digital Object(s) Each transcript has two versions - one in PDF and the other in MS Word.; 9.5 Megabytes
  - Ernst Frick to Else [von Richthofen], 1911; MS008.001.001.00053; Gross, Frieda (Box 1)
    Subject: Letter from Ernst Frick to Else, to be forwarded to Fredele [Gross] whom he has not been able to contact yet. Subject: travels to england. (Cafe Restaurant Americain Stationary)
  - [Frieda Gross] to Else [von Richthofen], 1911 -- 1912; MS008.001.001.00054; Gross, Frieda (Box 1)
    Subject: Freda is in a very bad emotional state, feeling life is senseless and she also feel that Ernst is losing strength as his trial draws near. There is an upcoming trial mentioned, probably the one for Ernst Frick. Freda does not know if she wants to attend it. Love makes life worth living. Mentions how aspects of life are to be perceived: happiness and despair are dual aspects of life. financial difficulties for Freda because of trial. looks forward to being with Ernst again but worries about the future. asks for books to keep Ernst company in jail.
  - [Frieda Gross] to Else [von Richthofen], 1911 -- 1912; MS008.001.001.00055; Gross, Frieda (Box 1)
    Subject: [Frieda] is pessimistic about her life and feels emotional pain. Mentions Alfred [Weber] and the children as Else's reason for happiness. talks about her emotional difficulties about an upcoming 2nd trial. asks for a temporary loan from Else to pay Dr. Skarvan MD of Bat. Austria, doesn't disclose the reason.
  - [Frieda Gross] to Else [von Richthofen], 1912; MS008.001.001.00056; Gross, Frieda (Box 1)
    Subject: Letter is a fragment. Expresses gratitude for the dresses which she received as a gift [for her daughter]. wants to get more information from Else about the developments that Friedele [V.R.] told her husband about her relation to Otto [Gross] and Ernst [Frick]. Is fatalistic about her own life.
  - Ernst [Frick] to Frieda [von Richthofen], 1912; MS008.001.001.00057; Gross, Frieda (Box 1)
    Subject: He does not want to see her while he is imprisoned. He occupies himself by contemplating essential ideas of life, like freedom. States that culture is decadent.
  - Friedel [Frieda Gross] to Else [von Richthofen], 1912; MS008.001.001.00058; Gross, Frieda (Box 1)
    Letter is a fragment. Subject: Thinks her mail is being opened--possibly involvements of the police. Talks about Brennwald, the attorneys whom she describes as money hungry and lazy and not informed about details of Ernst's case. Chances for a good outcome of Ernst's trial are slim, according to her. Mentions Paul's release from custody. Talks about Friedele's new love: Lawrence and wants to find out more about him.
  - Friedel [Frieda Gross] to Else [von Richthofen], 1912; MS008.001.001.00059; Gross, Frieda (Box 1)
    Subject: Tells what is going on with Ernst's trial. Feels that the court has some animosity toward Ernst and considers it unfair that they don't release him.
  - Friedel [Frieda Gross] to Else [von Richthofen], 1912 -- 1913; MS008.001.001.00060; Gross, Frieda (Box 1)
    Subject: Tells Else of her fondness of her. Ernst has been released from prison and has a hard time adjusting. Days later, Ernst has been arrested again for possession of explosives. She is in love with him again.
  - Friedel [Frieda Gross] to Else [von Richthofen], 1912; MS008.001.001.00061; Gross, Frieda (Box 1)
    Subject: Expresses the wish Else would visit her. Talks about her children and how she is even more in love with Ernst. Is sorry she can't meet with Emil Lask [Heidelberg Philosopher].
  - Friedel [Frieda Gross] to Bethel [Else von Richthofen]., MS008.001.001.00062; Gross, Frieda (Box 1)
    Letter is a fragment. Subject: She thanks her for the money and the telegram. Tells that she hates Otto [Gross] and expects horrible things from him.
  - Friedel [Frieda Gross] to Else [von Richthofen], 1912; MS008.001.001.00063; Gross, Frieda (Box 1)
    Subject: States, it would be dangerous for Otto to come to Switzerland, since the authorities would pick him up. She feels adversarial toward him, but doesn't want to have him as an enemy. In her imagination she is always expecting Ernst to show up. Concerns about the situation regarding the children.
  - [Frieda Gross] to Else [von Richthofen], 1913; MS008.001.001.00064; Gross, Frieda (Box 1)
    Letter is a fragment. Subject: She talks about her relationship with Ernst which depresses her and whom she hates now. Wants to borrow 5000 mark from Else for living expenses. Talks about having to give up the children. Tells of her nightmares and emotional state of panic.
  - Friedel [Frieda Gross] to Else [von Richthofen], MS008.001.001.00065; Gross, Frieda (Box 1)
    Letter is a fragment. Subject: States that it is shortly before a trial (unclear whose trial, possibly about losing their children.)
  - [Frieda Gross] to Else [von Richthofen, 1915; MS008.001.001.00066; Gross, Frieda (Box 1)
    Letter is a fragment. Subject: She is looking forward to a restful vacation in the mountains. Expects a visit from Else. Talks about Else's unfounded jealousy with respect to herself and Max Weber.
  - [Frieda Gross] to Else [von Richthofen], 1915; MS008.001.002.00067; Gross, Frieda (Box 2)
    Subject: She is overwhelmed by fear and feels that she is almost losing her mind. She talks about a person named Pellech (her lawyer) and a trial (concerning the children) that is coming to a close. Talks about her attitude toward life: her love to Peter [son] and Ernst [lover] and her suffering and feeling of depression. Fears Ernst could be leaving her.
  - [Frieda Gross] to Else [von Richthofen], 1915; MS008.001.002.00068; Gross, Frieda (Box 2)
    Subject: Expresses her compassion about the death of Else's son, Peter. She wants to come and comfort Else.
  - [Frieda Gross] to Else [von Richthofen], 1915; MS008.001.002.00069; Gross, Frieda (Box 2)
    Subject: Frieda wants to come and visit Else to comfort her [Else is in mourning about the loss of her son, Peter.] Talks to Otto [Gross] request for a divorce since he wants to get married again. Mentions her reservations about Otto's character.
  - [Frieda Gross] to Else [von Richthofen], 1915; MS008.001.002.00070; Gross, Frieda (Box 2)
    Subject: Frieda and her children have been ill and she can't come home for a visit therefore. Talks about the profound effect Peter's death had on her.
  - Friedel [Frieda Gross] to Else [von Richthofen], 1917; MS008.001.002.00071; Gross, Frieda (Box 2)
    Subject: She feels she couldn't write so much nonsense, since it is all due to the fact that she cannot master her life. Update on her family life. Talks about Else not living in Wolfratshausen anymore.
  - Friedel [Frieda Gross] to Else [von Richthofen], 1916; MS008.001.002.00072; Gross, Frieda (Box 2)
    Subject: Talks about her ideas about death in connection with Peter's death. Reflects on her life's changes and now she has to do all the house work herself, which tires her out. Mentions Else living in "Vogelnest" now (translated "Bird's nest").
  - Friedel [Frieda Gross] to Else [von Richthofen], 1917; MS008.001.002.00073; Gross, Frieda (Box 2)
    Subject: States that she doesn't have the strength to cope with daily life. She is exhausted and her nerves are ruined. Wants to know what's going on with Else.
  - Friedel [Frieda Gross] to Else [von Richthofen], 1919; MS008.001.002.00074; Gross, Frieda (Box 2)
    Subject: She thanks Else for her and Max Weber's financial help. States that her emotional pain and melancholy is a serious illness. Refers to Edgar [Jaffe] who seems to be hospitalized for the same illness. She was away for some rest and recooperation.
  - Friedel [Frieda Gross] to Else [von Richthofen], 1920; MS008.001.002.00075; Gross, Frieda (Box 2)
    Letter is a fragment. Subject: Informs Else of Otto [Gross'] death of pneumonia in Berlin. States, something big has come to a close without a solution (referring to Otto). Talks about financial troubles. Emphasizes that she is Peter Gross' guardian.
  - Friedel [Frieda Gross] to Else [von Richthofen], 1920; MS008.001.002.00076; Gross, Frieda (Box 2)
    Subject: States she had a nervous breakdown because of jealousy--probably because of Margarethe (Fellerer) whom she calls the devil's bride. Mentions Peter Wyneken as a possible way out of her problems. (Wyneken Operates an Experimental School.)
  - [Frieda Gross] to Else [von Richthofen], 1920; MS008.001.002.00077; Gross, Frieda (Box 2)
    Subject: She Thanks Else for gift of money. Mentions a Mrs von Strzgowsky from Graz, she is wealthy and full of vitality-- she left her husband and 6 children to live with an old friend of Otto [Gross]. Ernst whom she calls a failure in real life but "good like" is now a lover of Margarethe. She considers him a pathological case.
  - Friedel [Frieda Gross] to Else [von Richthofen], 1921; MS008.001.002.00078; Gross, Frieda (Box 2)
    Subject: Friedel considers her life and her relationship with Ernst [Frick] sad and almost desperate. Calls him paranoid. His attitude is very negative toward her. But she knows that she has strength to survive. Talks about the personality of her children.
  - Friedel [Frieda Gross] to Else [von Richthofen], 1921; MS008.001.002.00079; Gross, Frieda (Box 2)
    Subject: Frieda feels isolated-- her focus are only the children. Ernst eager to move to Arbe, Tyrol, an isolated island in Yugoslavia?--thinks it is better for him as a painter. [Heinrich] Goesch wants to come also. Frieda concerned about practical aspects of new life and schooling of children.
  - Friedel [Frieda Gross] to Else [von Richthofen], 1922; MS008.001.002.00080; Gross, Frieda (Box 2)
    Dark stains on paper. Subject: Frieda's relationship with Ernst is bad. He is hateful and paranoid toward her. She is trying to come to terms with this situation. Cornelia, her daughter, is very ill.
  - Friedel [Frieda Gross] to Else [von Richthofen], 1922; MS008.001.002.00081; Gross, Frieda (Box 2)
    Subject: They found out that Cornelia (daughter) has Tuberculosis. Friedel writes about her love and fear for this child.
  - Friedel [Frieda Gross] to Else [von Richthofen], 1922; MS008.001.002.00082; Gross, Frieda (Box 2)
    Subject: Frieda is hopeful about Cornelia's prognosis regarding her tuberculosis. She is emotionally and physically exhausted. Feels her situation with Ernst [Frick] cannot be solved.
  - M. [Marianne Weber]? to Else [von Richthofen], 1922; MS008.001.002.00083; Gross, Frieda (Box 2)
    Subject: Mentions (Edgar) Salin. Refers to Klages' writings with the title "Essence of Conciousness". She thinks they are more interesting than Jasper's. Talks about Miss Walther's ideas about phenomenalism.
  - Friedel [Frieda Gross] to Else [von Richthofen], 1922; MS008.001.002.00084; Gross, Frieda (Box 2)
    Subject: Friedel feels she is losing her identity because of Ernst's (Frick) tyrannical and fanatical behavior. Her love is dead. Relief that Ernst has left for Germany. Feels this disharmony is bad for the children. Refers to the difficult financial situation.
  - Friedel [Frieda Gross] to Else [von Richthofen], 1922; MS008.001.002.00085; Gross, Frieda (Box 2)
    Subject: Friedel tells about miserable living conditions in Ascona--she converted a stable into an apartment. She feels Ernst hates her and destroys her life. She longs for a visit with Else.
  - Friedel [Frieda Gross] to Else [von Richthofen], 1923; MS008.001.002.00086; Gross, Frieda (Box 2)
    Subject: Refers to a possible marriage between Ernst [Frick] and Margarethe. She fears he would want to take the children from her claiming that she is intellectually and morally unfit to be a mother. States that Ernst made her life miserable.
  - Friedel [Frieda Gross] to Else [von Richthofen], 1930; MS008.001.002.00087; Gross, Frieda (Box 2)
    Subject: Refers to her emotional suffering that manifests itself physically. Refers to some financial support from her brothers. Feels Else's relationship with Alfred is very fortunate.
  - Friedel [Frieda Gross] to Else [von Richthofen], 1930; MS008.001.002.00088; Gross, Frieda (Box 2)
    Subject: Friedel is concerned about her son's (Peter's) health. He is in Else's care and she is grateful. Refers to meeting Marianne Weber and is impressed with her self assurance and her sense of unity.
  - Friedel [Frieda Gross] to Else [von Richthofen], 1940; MS008.001.002.00089; Gross, Frieda (Box 2)
    Subject: Talks about her childrens' life and her own emotional state, which seems in harmony with nature.
  - Friedel [Frieda Gross] to Else [von Richthofen], 1941; MS008.001.002.00090; Gross, Frieda (Box 2)
    Subject: Concerned about Peter's and Eva's health (possibly tuberculosis). Talks about her and Else's common part. books are her only relief from her anxieties.
  - Friedel [Frieda Gross] to Else [von Richthofen], 1942 -- 1943; MS008.001.002.00091; Gross, Frieda (Box 2)
    Note: Blue ink stains on both sheets. Subject: She talks about her philosophy of life and the importance of the right attitude toward it. Great concern about Peter's health. The other children are helping to support him even though they are hardly getting by themselves.
  - Eva [Gross] to Else [von Richthofen], 1943; MS008.001.002.00092; Gross, Frieda (Box 2)
    Subject: Talks about her mother being very ill and how all the children and Ernst [Frick] are caring for her. Praises her mother.
  - Friedel [Frieda Gross] to Else [von Richthofen], 1946; MS008.001.002.00093; Gross, Frieda (Box 2)
    Subject: Reminisces about her admiration and gratitude and love for Else. Peter her son is a physician now.
  - Friedel [Frieda Gross] to Else [von Richthofen], 1947; MS008.001.002.00094; Gross, Frieda (Box 2)
    Subject: Speaks about her own life in a melancholic way. Prays for a peaceful death. Refers to her children's life as hard and sad. She lost her house in Bosco and lives in a rooming house. Talks about her loneliness and hopelessness despite Limsero (a man).
  - Friedel [Frieda Gross] to Else [von Richthofen], 1947; MS008.001.002.00095; Gross, Frieda (Box 2)
    Subject: Refers to her children Peter and Cornelia-- both are very sick (possibly tuberculosis).
  - Friedl [Frieda Gross] to Bethel [Else von Richthofen], MS008.001.002.00096; Gross, Frieda (Box 2)
    Letter is a fragment. Frieda expresses her love for Else. She talks about the dilemma between her passion for life and her lack of physical strength. Her "sciatic leg" is being treated with arsenic and iron. Mentions a relationship with Rupprecht which she views as real, good, adna lasting.
  - Friedl [Frieda Gross] to Bethel [Else von Richthofen], MS008.001.002.00097; Gross, Frieda (Box 2)
    In this letter Frieda states her enormous suffering due to her "neuralgic leg." The pain is unbearable in spite of the medication (morphine, chloroform, bromine, and electroshocks). Else seems to be a beacon of happiness in her life. She refers to herself as a spiritual and physical cripple, no longer human.
  - [Frieda Gross] to Bethel [Else von Richthofen], MS008.001.002.00098; Gross, Frieda (Box 2)
    Letter is a fragment. She states that Tyrol is becoming a Goggingen for her. She mentions her enduring love for the factory inspector [Else] and talks about trivial things.
  - Friedl [Frieda Gross] to Bethel [Else von Richthofen], March 21, MS008.001.002.00099; Gross, Frieda (Box 2)
    Fragment. Frieda refers to the terrible news about Schlussar and how we seem to worry about trivialities. She announces that they are moving to Glacisstrasse, an elegant apartment. She is looking forward to playing her new piano there. [Correspondence Frieda Gross - Else von Richthofen continues with #200]
  - Otto Gross to Else von Richthofen, 1907; MS008.001.002.00100; Gross, Otto (Box 2)
    He talks about their fragile friendship - their happiness was perfect in the past. He is concerned her feelings for him have changed and wants a truthful basis between them. He mentions a surgeon as a possible rival [this refers to Volcker]. He talks about the social class system. He is waiting for her call if she still has the same feelings for him. [1 sheet partially torn.]
  - Otto Gross to Else [von Richthofen], MS008.001.002.00101; Gross, Otto (Box 2)
    He is concerned about her silence and worries about her feelings for him. He distances himself from Schiemann who asked Edgar (Else's husband) for money.
  - Otto Gross to Else [von Richthofen], 1907; MS008.001.002.00102; Gross, Otto (Box 2)
    He mentions that he is involved in a rehab program [probably regarding his drug addiction] and he asks for her love and support. He hopes to get together as soon as he has improved.
  - Otto Gross to Else [von Richthofen], MS008.001.002.00103; Gross, Otto (Box 2)
    He tells how enraptured he was about her phone call and how he could feel her presence. He contrasts he friendship and dependability with the unreliability of passion. He talks about his ideas of eroticism.
  - Otto Gross to Else [von Richthofen], MS008.001.002.00104; Gross, Otto (Box 2)
    He considers her letter as a document of her love to him. He refers to the wonderful times they enjoyed at the country house. Describes the strength and pefection of their love, since she does not object to him loving her sister as well.
  - Otto Gross to Else [von Richthofen], MS008.001.002.00105; Gross, Otto (Box 2)
    He talks with melancholy about their love and happiness. How perfect they were and their transitory aspects. He feels he will always be tied to her. [Second page torn.]
  - Otto Gross to Else [von Richthofen], MS008.001.002.00106; Gross, Otto (Box 2)
    He talks about his great love for her and the positive influence her love had on his life and work. He has moved on beyond Nietzsche and Freud. She gave him confidence and energy with her trusting love to overcome his resignation. Iriedel [Frieda Weekley] has given him joyful hope as well. No date available
  - Otto Gross to Else [von Richthofen], 1907; MS008.001.002.00107; Gross, Otto (Box 2)
    Refers to M. [probably Muhsam, friend of Otto Gross and lover of Frieda Gross] with whom he got together at the [Cafe] Stephanie. Otto mentions that some matter with M. have come to a close. [Postcard.]
  - Otto [Gross] to Else [von Richthofen], 1907; MS008.001.002.00108; Gross, Otto (Box 2)
    Otto expresses his concern for Else and mentions his big hope [probably their child that Else is expecting.] Mentions Frieda [Gross] who has just given birth and who is with M. (Muhsam her lover). States he doesn't believe in complete happiness.
  - Else [von Richthofen] to Otto [Gross], 1907; MS008.001.002.00109; Von Richthofen, Else (Box 2)
    She criticizes his attitude toward women who love him - referring to Frieda Gross. He does not see them as individuals but only wants followers of his teachings. She claims that his productivity and judgment may have suffered from his morphine addiction.
  - Otto [Gross] to Else [Von Richthofen], MS008.001.002.00110; Gross, Otto (Box 2)
    Letter is a fragment (page 6 of a missing letter). He is referring to the possibility of Edgar [Jaffe's] love to Else coming to an end, since he feels that Edgar was incompatible with Else. This implies more hope for their own love. No date available
  - Hanns Gross (?) to Otto [Gross], MS008.001.002.00111; Gross, Hanns (Box 2)
    Hanns (Otto's father) is asking Otto to edit a paper of his and gives instructions about the format. No date available
  - Friedal [Frieda Gross] to Otto [Gross], 1907; MS008.001.002.00112; Gross, Frieda (Box 2)
    Postcard (that someone has scribbled over). She talks about being with Muhsam instead of Peterle on this day.
  - Ernest [Weekly] to Else [Von Richthofen], 1900; MS008.001.002.00113; Weekly, Ernest (Box 2)
    A congratulatory note to Else [v. R] on earning her doctorate in Heidelberg. (language is English)
  - Ernest [Weekly] to Else [Von Richthofen], 1898; MS008.001.002.00114; Weekly, Ernest (Box 2)
    He talks about his love and happiness with Freida [Weekly, his wife] and how he admires the nobility of her character. (language is English)
  - Ernest [Weekly] to Else [Von Richthofen], 1900; MS008.001.002.00115; Weekly, Ernest (Box 2)
    He praises Else's achievements in her new post for the government of Baden. Mentions his new born son. Invites her for a visit to Nottingham. (language is English)
  - Freida [Von Richthofen] to Else [Von Richthofen], MS008.001.002.00116; Von Richthofen, Freida (Box 2)
    She mentions a common acquaintance named Goldsmith whom Else has met [recently]. She talks about her happy family life. Encourages Else to continue her work after she is married. No date available
  - Freida [Von Richthofen] to Else [Von Richthofen], MS008.001.002.00117; Von Richthofen, Freida (Box 2)
    She tells Else [her sister] that she feels great respect for her. She expects Else's lifestyle to be grand and that she will be wealthy. Mentions a person named Moubart. No date available
  - Freiderike [Freida Von Richthofen] to Else [Von Richthofen], MS008.001.002.00118; Von Richthofen, Freida (Box 2)
    She talks about family and social matters. She feels the need for help with the care of her baby since she considers herself ignorant about it. Asks Else to purchase an appliance [burner, heater ?] for her. No date available
  - Freida [Von Richthofen] to Else [Von Richthofen], MS008.001.002.00119; Von Richthofen, Freida (Box 2)
    Mentions Behling, who is in love. Luisa and Johanna are involved in the situation. Mention M. who loves her. Explains her relationship with Kurth-feels superior to him. States ahe was always true to herself in her emotions and has no guilty feelings. No date available
  - Freida [Von Richthofen] to Else [Von Richthofen], 1898; MS008.001.002.00120; Von Richthofen, Freida (Box 2)
    Refers to Behling's relationship with Hannele. Freida finds the secrecy that surrounds it distasteful. Mentions that her health is not too good. Had dinner alone with M. Rohr -- felt uncomfortable about it.
  - Fritzle [Freida Von Richthofen ?] to Else [Von Richthofen], 1898; MS008.001.003.00121; Von Richthofen, Freida (Box 3)
    Mentions Helene and Karoline who visited her. She doesn't believe in her own infallible virtue anymore, since the affair with Kammacher. States her fondness for her sister, who will be visiting Graz.
  - Edgar [Jaffe] to wife [Else Von Richthofen], MS008.001.003.00122; Jaffe, Edgar (Box 3)
    Edgar is relating Otto [Gross's] query regarding a possible change of Else's feelings toward Otto. Otto wants to know if this was related to Else's experience with V. [Volcker ?] or a result of her naturaal inclination toward a principle that is hostile toward him. Edgar suspects that Else has other reasons. No date available
  - Freidel [Freida Gross] to Else [Von Richthofen], 1914; MS008.001.003.00123; Gross, Frieda (Box 3)
    Friedel is inquiring about Else's life during these difficult times of war. She expresses her own feelings about the war and dying
  - Freida [Von Richthofen] to her mother [Von Richthofen], MS008.001.003.00124; Von Richthofen, Freida (Box 3)
    Reports that Ernst, her husband is ill caused by his big, bad nerves. Tells about the good times and good relationship she has had with her mother-in-law Weekly. Refers to a certain (possibly questionable) behavior by her sister-in-law Edith, who is acting like "Boll". No date available
  - Sofie [Riehl] her aunt to Freidl [Freida Gross], MS008.001.003.00125; Riehl, Sofie (Box 3)
    She talks about her love for Freida and that she cannot yet disclose the reasons for not writing.
  - Sofie [Riehl] her aunt to Freidl [Freida Gross], 1908; MS008.001.003.00126; Riehl, Sofie (Box 3)